<doc sitename="Clarkesworld Magazine" title="Clarkesworld Magazine - Science Fiction &amp; Fantasy" author="Neil Clarke" date="2022-01-01" source="https://clarkesworldmagazine.com/clarke_01_12/" hostname="clarkesworldmagazine.com" excerpt="Clarkesworld Science Fiction and Fantasy Magazine and Podcast. This page: 2011 Reader's Poll" categories="" tags="" fingerprint="7lVbmnCwK0V4QLz5Ji1RrYJyu7o=">
  <main>
    <p>Editorial</p>
    <head rend="h1">2011 Reader's Survey</head>
    <p>Every year, we give you the opportunity to pick your Clarkesworld favorites from the prior year. This time around, you'll have the opportunity to select your favorite story and cover art from 2011, as well as give us a little feedback. Feel free to use the comments on this post to help promote your favorites. (No attacking other people's choices.)</p>
    <p>This survey will close on January 30th and the results will be published in our February issue.</p>
    <head rend="h2">2011 Fiction</head>
    <list>
      <item>Ghostweight by Yoon Ha Lee</item>
      <item>Tying Knots by Ken Liu</item>
      <item>Diving After the Moon by Rachel Swirsky</item>
      <item>Three Oranges by D. Elizabeth Wasden</item>
      <item>The Book of Phoenix (Excerpted from The Great Book) by Nnedi Okorafor</item>
      <item>Perfect Lies by Gwendolyn Clare</item>
      <item>The Cartographer Wasps and the Anarchist Bees by E. Lily Yu</item>
      <item>Matchmaker by Erin M. Hartshorn</item>
      <item>Whose Face This Is I Do Not Know by Cat Rambo</item>
      <item>The Architect of Heaven by Jason K. Chapman</item>
      <item>Semiramis by Genevieve Valentine</item>
      <item>Trickster by Mari Ness</item>
      <item>Trois morceaux en forme de mechanika by Gord Sellar</item>
      <item>Frozen Voice by An Owomoyela</item>
      <item>Conservation of Shadows by Yoon Ha Lee</item>
      <item>The Fish of Lijiang by Chen Qiufan</item>
      <item>Pack by Robert Reed</item>
      <item>Signals in the Deep by Greg Mellor</item>
      <item>Staying Behind by Ken Liu</item>
      <item>Pony by Erik Amundsen</item>
      <item>Silently and Very Fast by Catherynne M. Valente</item>
      <item>A Militant Peace by David Klecha and Tobias S. Buckell</item>
      <item>The Smell of Orange Groves by Lavie Tidhar</item>
      <item>In Which Faster-Than-Light Travel Solves All of Our Problems by Chris Stabback</item>
      <item>Sirius by Ben Peek</item>
    </list>
    <head rend="h2">Cover Art</head>
    <p>Neil Clarke is the editor of Clarkesworld Magazine and Forever Magazine; owner of Wyrm Publishing; and a ten-time Hugo Award Nominee for Best Editor (short form). His anthologies include Upgraded, Galactic Empires, More Human Than Human, Touchable Unreality, The Final Frontier, Not One of Us, The Eagle has Landed, and the Best Science Fiction of the Years series. His latest anthology, The Best Science Fiction of the Year: Volume 6, is now available from Night Shade Books. He currently lives in NJ with his wife and two sons.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>