<doc sitename="Clarkesworld Magazine" title="Clarkesworld Magazine - Science Fiction &amp; Fantasy" author="Neil Clarke" date="2022-01-01" source="https://clarkesworldmagazine.com/2009_readers_poll/" hostname="clarkesworldmagazine.com" excerpt="Clarkesworld Science Fiction and Fantasy Magazine and Podcast. This page: 2009 Clarkesworld Reader's Poll" categories="" tags="" fingerprint="uN1Ln6o4UiZR8YzglpyaQqNDxgg=">
  <main>
    <p>Editorial</p>
    <head rend="h1">2009 Reader's Poll</head>
    <p>Every year, we give you the opportunity to pick your Clarkesworld favorites from the prior year. This time around, we are focusing on your favorite fiction and cover art from 2009 (listed below).</p>
    <p>Everyone that participates will be in the running for one of five free copies of UNPLUGGED: THE WEB'S BEST SCI-FI &amp; FANTASY: 2008 DOWNLOAD, a new trade paperback from Wyrm Publishing.</p>
    <p>We will close this survey on January 30th and publish the results in our next issue.</p>
    <head rend="h2">2009 Fiction</head>
    <list>
      <item>Celadon by Desirina Boskovich</item>
      <item>Teaching Bigfoot to Read by Geoffrey W. Cole</item>
      <item>The Second Gift Given by Ken Scholes</item>
      <item>The Jisei of Mark VIII by Berrien C. Henderson</item>
      <item>Herding Vegetable Sheep by Ekaterina Sedia</item>
      <item>The Loyalty of Birds by Rachel Sobel</item>
      <item>Rolling Steel: A Pre-Apocalyptic Love Story by Jay Lake and Shannon Page</item>
      <item>The Dying World by Lavie Tidhar</item>
      <item>From the Lost Diary of TreeFrog7 by Nnedi Okorafor</item>
      <item>The Devonshire Arms by Alex Dally MacFarlane</item>
      <item>Walking with a Ghost by Nick Mamatas</item>
      <item>The Giving Heart by Corie Ralston</item>
      <item>Placa del Fuego by Tobias S. Buckell</item>
      <item>On the Lot and In the Air by Lisa Hannett</item>
      <item>The Radiant Car Thy Sparrows Drew by Catherynne M. Valente</item>
      <item>Advection by Genevieve Valentine</item>
      <item>White Charles by Sarah Monette</item>
      <item>Non-Zero Probabilities by N.K. Jemisin</item>
      <item>Spar by Kij Johnson</item>
      <item>Of Melei, of Ulthar by Gord Sellar</item>
      <item>The Mermaids Singing Each to Each by Cat Rambo</item>
      <item>Brief Candle by Jason K. Chapman</item>
      <item>Night, in Dark Perfection by Richard Parks</item>
      <item>The Grandmother-Granddaughter Conspiracy by Marissa Lingen</item>
    </list>
    <head rend="h2">2009 Cover Art</head>
    <p>Neil Clarke is the editor of Clarkesworld Magazine and Forever Magazine; owner of Wyrm Publishing; and a ten-time Hugo Award Nominee for Best Editor (short form). His anthologies include Upgraded, Galactic Empires, More Human Than Human, Touchable Unreality, The Final Frontier, Not One of Us, The Eagle has Landed, and the Best Science Fiction of the Years series. His latest anthology, The Best Science Fiction of the Year: Volume 6, is now available from Night Shade Books. He currently lives in NJ with his wife and two sons.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>