<doc sitename="Clarkesworld Magazine" title="Clarkesworld Magazine - Science Fiction &amp; Fantasy" author="Neil Clarke" date="2022-01-01" source="https://clarkesworldmagazine.com/clarke_01_16/" hostname="clarkesworldmagazine.com" excerpt="Clarkesworld Science Fiction and Fantasy Magazine and Podcast. This page: Editor's Desk: The 2015 Reader's Poll and Contest by Neil Clarke" categories="" tags="" fingerprint="jzXtJXBPIRUMV3wOPCKphwIi+c4=">
  <main>
    <p>Editorial</p>
    <head rend="h1">Editor's Desk: The 2015 Reader's Poll and Contest</head>
    <p>It’s time for our annual reader’s poll! Each year, we ask you to pick your favorite Clarkesworld story and cover art. Here’s a complete list of the original fiction we published in 2015:</p>
    <list>
      <item>“A Universal Elegy” by Tang Fei</item>
      <item>“All Original Brightness” by Mike Buckley</item>
      <item>“An Evolutionary Myth” by Bo-young Kim</item>
      <item>“An Exile of the Heart” by Jay Lake</item>
      <item>“And If the Body Were Not the Soul” by A.C. Wise</item>
      <item>“Android Whores Can’t Cry” by Natalia Theodoridou</item>
      <item>“Asymptotic” by Andy Dudak</item>
      <item>“Cassandra” by Ken Liu</item>
      <item>“Cat Pictures Please” by Naomi Kritzer</item>
      <item>“Coming of the Light” by Chen Qiufan</item>
      <item>“Cremulator” by Robert Reed</item>
      <item>“Egg Island” by Karen Heuler</item>
      <item>“Ether” by Zhang Ran</item>
      <item>“For the Love of Sylvia City” by Andrea M. Pawley</item>
      <item>“Forestspirit, Forestspirit” by Bogi Takács</item>
      <item>“Further North” by Kay Chronister</item>
      <item>“Ice” by Rich Larson</item>
      <item>“If on a Winter’s Night a Traveler” by Xia Jia</item>
      <item>“In the Queue for the Worldship Munawwer” by Sara Saab</item>
      <item>“Indelible” by Gwendolyn Clare</item>
      <item>“It Was Educational” by J.B. Park</item>
      <item>“Let Baser Things Devise” by Berrien C. Henderson</item>
      <item>“Loving Grace” by Erica L. Satifka</item>
      <item>“Meshed” by Rich Larson</item>
      <item>“Morrigan in Shadow” by Seth Dickinson</item>
      <item>“Mrs. Griffin Prepares to Suicide Tonight” by A Que</item>
      <item>“Ossuary” by Ian Muneshwar</item>
      <item>“Postcards from Monster Island” by Emily Devenport</item>
      <item>“Preserve Her Memory” by Baoshu</item>
      <item>“Security Check” by Han Song</item>
      <item>“Slowly Builds An Empire” by Naim Kabir</item>
      <item>“Snakes” by Yoon Ha Lee</item>
      <item>“So Much Cooking” by Naomi Kritzer</item>
      <item>“Somewhere I Have Never Traveled (Third Sound Remix)” by E. Catherine Tobler</item>
      <item>“Summer at Grandma’s House” by Hao Jingfang</item>
      <item>“The Algebra of Events” by Elizabeth Bourne</item>
      <item>“The Apartment Dweller’s Bestiary” by Kij Johnson</item>
      <item>“The Empress in Her Glory” by Robert Reed</item>
      <item>“The Father” by Kola Heyward-Rotimi</item>
      <item>“The Garden Beyond Her Infinite Skies” by Matthew Kressel</item>
      <item>“The Hexagonal Bolero of Honeybees” by Krista Hoeppner Leahy</item>
      <item>“The Hunger Tower” by Pan Haitian</item>
      <item>“The Last Surviving Gondola Widow” by Kristine Kathryn Rusch</item>
      <item>“The Long Goodnight of Violet Wild” by Catherynne M. Valente</item>
      <item>“The Occidental Bride” by Benjanun Sriduangkaew</item>
      <item>“The Petals Abide” by Benjanun Sriduangkaew</item>
      <item>“The Servant” by Emily Devenport</item>
      <item>“The Three Resurrections of Jessica Churchill” by Kelly Robson</item>
      <item>“This Wanderer, in the Dark of the Year” by Kris Millering</item>
      <item>“Three Cups of Grief, by Starlight” by Aliette de Bodard</item>
      <item>“Today I am Paul” by Martin Shoemaker</item>
      <item>“Union” by Tamsyn Muir</item>
      <item>“When We Die on Mars” by Cassandra Khaw</item>
      <item>“When Your Child Strays From God” by Sam J. Miller</item>
      <item>“Your Right Arm” by Nin Harris</item>
      <item>“Yuanyuan’s Bubbles” by Liu Cixin</item>
    </list>
    <p>And here’s a quick round-up of our 2015 covers:</p>
    <p>As an added incentive for participating, we’re giving away copies of Clarkesworld: Year Eight (publishing this month) to three lucky voters!</p>
    <p>The survey will be online now through February 23rd, with the results being announced in our March issue. You can take the survey at http://clarkesworld2015.questionpro.com.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>