<doc sitename="Clarkesworld Magazine" title="Clarkesworld Magazine - Science Fiction &amp; Fantasy" author="Neil Clarke" date="2022-01-01" source="https://clarkesworldmagazine.com/contest_09_09/" hostname="clarkesworldmagazine.com" excerpt="Clarkesworld Science Fiction and Fantasy Magazine and Podcast. This page: September Contest : Free Books!" categories="" tags="" fingerprint="3frs4ibImRWaV6MA7YkPyZxBkho=">
  <main>
    <p>Editorial</p>
    <head rend="h1">September Contest : Free Books!</head>
    <p>This month, we have an opportunity for our readers to pick up one of two new books:</p>
    <p>Paul McAuley, author of this month's non-fiction article, is celebrating the US release of The Quiet War, and courtesy of Pyr, we have five copies to give away to our readers.</p>
    <p>A small box of Advance Reading Copies of next Clarkesworld anthology, Realms 2, recently landed on our doorstep. These are the uncorrected copies we send off to reviewers, but we thought some of our readers would appreciate a chance to get the early edition. We have three of these available for this competition.</p>
    <p>All you have to do to be eligible is post a link to this month's issue on your blog, Facebook, or Twitter and then come back here and give us a link to your post/tweet in a comment to this post. Eight times this September, we'll pick a winner at random (my six-year-old is a great random number generator).</p>
    <p>If you're selected, you get to pick one book from the pile of remaining books. To be fair to others, once you win, you're out of the competition for the rest of the month.</p>
    <p>Good luck!</p>
    <p>Winners: Neil Clarke is the editor of Clarkesworld Magazine and Forever Magazine; owner of Wyrm Publishing; and a ten-time Hugo Award Nominee for Best Editor (short form). His anthologies include Upgraded, Galactic Empires, More Human Than Human, Touchable Unreality, The Final Frontier, Not One of Us, The Eagle has Landed, and the Best Science Fiction of the Years series. His latest anthology, The Best Science Fiction of the Year: Volume 6, is now available from Night Shade Books. He currently lives in NJ with his wife and two sons.</p>
    <list>
      <item>Dr Paisley - Selected Realms 2</item>
      <item>Isobel - Selected The Quiet War</item>
      <item>Sarah - Selected Realms 2</item>
      <item>Danielle - Selected Realms 2 (all copies gone)</item>
      <item>TBA</item>
      <item>TBA</item>
      <item>TBA</item>
      <item>TBA</item>
    </list>
    <p>Neil Clarke is the editor of Clarkesworld Magazine and Forever Magazine; owner of Wyrm Publishing; and a ten-time Hugo Award Nominee for Best Editor (short form). His anthologies include Upgraded, Galactic Empires, More Human Than Human, Touchable Unreality, The Final Frontier, Not One of Us, The Eagle has Landed, and the Best Science Fiction of the Years series. His latest anthology, The Best Science Fiction of the Year: Volume 6, is now available from Night Shade Books. He currently lives in NJ with his wife and two sons.</p>
  </main>
  <comments/>
</doc>